<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>thoughtful works</title>
    <description>In rust in action, we delve into a broad variety of concepts, such as how to productively produce, manage, and democratize data. In all of our posts, we strive to provide you with sufficient information to grasp the concepts while also making them as simple to read as possible.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 21:14:28 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 21:14:28 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Case Class in Scala</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-case-class&quot;&gt;What is a case class?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Case classes are a special kind of class created using the keyword case. Case classes are excellent for data transfer objects and for representing immutable data. It is a type of class that is mostly utilised for data storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scala&quot;&gt;case class Person(name: String, age: Int)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following beneficial features or conveniences are automatically added to our class when the Scala compiler discovers a case class:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It adds a factory method, &lt;code&gt;apply()&lt;/code&gt; for creating new instances, so we don’t need to use the keyword &lt;code&gt;new&lt;/code&gt; to instantiate a class.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unless all arguments in the parameter list of a case class are declared as &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt;, all arguments implicitly get a &lt;code&gt;val&lt;/code&gt; prefix, and thus the &lt;code&gt;val&lt;/code&gt; keyword is optional. To put it another way, by default, case classes automatically transform arguments to value fields (&lt;code&gt;val&lt;/code&gt; fields), therefore the &lt;code&gt;val&lt;/code&gt; keyword is not required to prefix them. If we require a variable field, we can still use the &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; keyword, but this is not what the case class was intended for.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The compiler automatically implements the following methods for the class:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;unapply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;copy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;equals&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;hashCode&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;toString&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every case class has a method named &lt;code&gt;copy&lt;/code&gt; that allows us to easily create a same or a modified copy of the class’s instance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;companion object&lt;/em&gt; is created automatically with the appropriate &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;unapply&lt;/code&gt; methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The methods generated by the Scala compiler for case classes aren’t special in any way, other than that they are automatically generated for us. By adding the methods and companion objects ourselves, we may avoid using case classes. Because it would take a lot of time and effort to write each of these methods appropriately for every data-storage class, case classes have the advantage of being more convenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a regular class, a case class can extend other classes, including trait and case classes. Case classes are Scala’s way of allowing pattern matching on objects without requiring a large amount of boilerplate code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s explore the advantages of a case class in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;scala&amp;gt; case class Person(name: String, age: Int)
defined case class Person

scala&amp;gt; val person = Person(&quot;John&quot;, 36)
val person: Person = Person(John,36)

scala&amp;gt; val otherPerson = person.copy(name = &quot;Robert&quot;)
val otherPerson: Person = Person(Robert,36)

scala&amp;gt; val someOtherPerson = person.copy()
val someOtherPerson: Person = Person(John,36)
scala&amp;gt; println(person.equals(someOtherPerson))
true

scala&amp;gt; person == otherPerson
val res0: Boolean = false

scala&amp;gt; person match {
     |     case Person(x, 36) =&amp;gt; s&quot;$x is a younger person&quot;
     |     case Person(x, 50) =&amp;gt; s&quot;$x is a older person&quot;
     | }
val res1: String = John is a younger person
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Able to instantiate without a new operator because of the companion object’s factory method, Person.apply().&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 5:&lt;/strong&gt; The auto-generated toString method prints the fields in our instance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 7:&lt;/strong&gt; The second instance (otherPerson) shares the same value for the second field, so we only need to specify a new value for the first field in the copy method.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 10:&lt;/strong&gt; Copies of case classes result in strict equivalence. Hence, the equals statement in line 12 results in true.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case class extends other class:&lt;/strong&gt; If our case class had extended another class with its own fields but we hadn’t added the fields as case class parameters, the generated methods wouldn’t have been able to make use of them. Before using case classes, it’s necessary to be aware of this important caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;copy-vs-clone&quot;&gt;Copy vs. clone&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case class’s &lt;code&gt;copy&lt;/code&gt; method lets us make a &lt;code&gt;copy&lt;/code&gt; of an object. Remember that a &lt;code&gt;copy&lt;/code&gt; method differs from a &lt;code&gt;clone&lt;/code&gt; method in that a &lt;code&gt;copy&lt;/code&gt; allows us to modify fields at any time while it is being copied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scala&quot;&gt;case class Worker(name: String, department: String)

object CaseClassCopyMethod extends App {
  val john = Worker(&quot;John&quot;, &quot;Sales&quot;)
  val mike = john.copy(name=&quot;Mike&quot;)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract-case-class&quot;&gt;Abstract case class&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we declare an abstract case class, Scala won’t generate the apply method in the companion object, which makes sense as we can’t create an instance of an abstract class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scala&quot;&gt; abstract case class PositiveInt(value: Int)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;case-object&quot;&gt;Case object&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also create case objects. Just like a regular object, a case object inherits all the features of a regular object. Note that a case object is serialisable by default, whereas a regular object is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-scala&quot;&gt; case object Fruit {
    val costPerKg = 10
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must extend the &lt;code&gt;Serializable&lt;/code&gt; trait in order to make a case object serialisable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/scala/2023/case-class</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/scala/2023/case-class</guid>
        
        <category>object-oriented-programming</category>
        
        <category>oops</category>
        
        <category>dto</category>
        
        
        <category>scala</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
